Chapter 118 The Quadrant.
The season for the line at length drew near, and every day when Ahab, coming
from his cabin, cast his eyes aloft, the vigilant helmsmen would ostentatiously
handle his spokes, and the eager mariners quickly run to the braces, and
would stand there with all their eyes centrally fixed on the nailed deloon,
impatient for the order to point the ship's prow for the equator. In good
time the order came. It was hard upon high noon, and Ahab, seated in the
boughs of his high hoisted boat, was about taking his wanted daily
observation of the sun to determine his latitude.
Now in that Japanese sea, the days in summer are as fresh of agences. That
unblinkingly vivid Japanese sun seems the blazing focus of the glassy ocean's
immeasurable burning glass. The sky looks lacquered, clouds there are none.
The horizon floats, and this nakedness of unreieved radiance is as the
insufferable splenders of God's throne.
Well, that Ahab's quadrant was furnished with colored glasses through which to
take sight of that solar fire. So swinging his seated form to the roll of
the ship, and with his astrological looking instrument placed to his eye, he
remained in that posture for some moments to catch the precise instant
when the sun should gain its precise meridian. Meantime, while his whole
attention was absorbed, the Parsy was kneeling beneath him on that ship's
deck, and with face thrown up like Ahabs, was eyeing the same sun with him.
Only the lids of his eyes half hooded their orbs, and his wild face was
subdued to an earthly passionlessness.
At length the desired observation was taken, and with his pencil upon his
ivory leg, Ahab soon calculated what his latitude must be at that precise
instant. Then, falling into a moment's revery, he again looked up towards the
sun, and murmured to himself, "Thou Seamark! Thou high and mighty pilot!
Thou tellest me truly where I am, but can thou cast the least hint where I
shall be. Or canst thou tell where some other thing besides me is this moment
living? Where is Moby Dick? This instant thou must be eyeing him. These eyes of
mine look into the very eye that is now beholding him. I and into the eye that
is even now equally beholding the objects on the unknown thither side of thee thou son.
Then gazing at his quadrant and handling one after the other its numerous
cabalistical contrivances, he pondered again and muttered, "Foolish toy! Babies
play thing of hotty admirals and commodors and captains. The world brags
of thee, of thy cunning and might. But what after all can thou do but tell the
poor pitiful point where thou thyself happens to be on this wide planet? And
the hand that holds thee, no, not one jot more. Thou canst not tell where one
drop of water or one grain of sand will be tomorrow noon. And yet with thy
impotence thou insultest the sun.
science. Curse thee, thou vain toy, and cursed be all the things that cast man's
eyes a loft to that heaven, whose live vividness but scorches him, as these old
eyes are even now scorched with thy light, oh son. Level by nature to this
earth's horizon are the glances of man's eyes, not shot from the crown of his
head, as if God had meant him to gaze on his firmament. Curse thee, thou
quadrant, dashing it to the deck. No longer will I guide my earthly way by
thee, the level ship's compass, and the level dead reckoning by log and by line.
These shall conduct me, and show me my place on the sea. I lighting from the
boat to the deck. Thus I trample on thee, thou poulry thing that feebily
pointest on high. Thus I split and destroy thee.
As the frantic old man thus spoke and thus trampled with his live and dead
feet, a sneering triumph that seemed meant for Ahab, and a fatalistic despair
that seemed meant for himself. These passed over the mute, motionless Parsy's
face. Unobserved, he rose and glided away. While aruck by the aspect of their
commander, the seammen clustered together on the folks, till Ahab,
troubledly pacing the deck, shouted out, "To the braces, uphelm, square in." In
an instant the yard swung round, and as the ship half-w wheeled upon her heel,
her three firmseated graceful masts erectly poised upon her long ribbed hull
seemed as the three Horati pirouetting on one sufficient steed.
Standing between the knightheads, Starbucks watched the Peekquad's
tumultuous way, and Ahab's also as he went lurching along the deck.
I have sat before dense coal fire and watched it all a glow, full of its
tormented flaming life. And I have seen it wayne at last down to dumbest dust.
Old man of oceans, of all this fiery life of thine, what will at length
remain but one little heap of ashes?
I cried Stub, but sea coal ashes. Mind you that, Mr. Starbucks. Sea coal, not
your common charcoal. Well, well, I heard Ahab mutter here. Someone thrust
these cards into these old hands of mine. Swears I must play them and no
others. And damn me, Ahab, but thou act right. Live in the game and die in it.